part 1 chapter 7.
If there is hope, wrote Winston, it lies in the pros
If there was hope, it must lie in the polls because only there, in those
swarming disregarded masses, 85 percent of the population of Oceania, could the
force to destroy the Party ever be generated.
The Party could not be overthrown from within.
Its enemies, if it had any enemies, had no way of coming together or even of
identifying one another.
Even if the legendary Brotherhood existed, as just possibly it might,
it was inconceivable that its members could ever assemble in larger numbers
than twos and threes.
Rebellion meant a look in the eyes, an inflection of the voice; at the most, an
occasional whispered word.
But the proles, if only they could somehow become conscious of their own
strength, would have no need to conspire.
They needed only to rise up and shake themselves like a horse shaking off flies.
If they chose they could blow the Party to pieces tomorrow morning.
Surely sooner or later it must occur to them to do it?
And yet— He remembered how once he had been walking down a crowded street when a
tremendous shout of hundreds of voices— women's voices— —had burst from a side
street a little way ahead.
It was a great formidable cry of anger and despair, a deep loud oh that went
Hamming on like the reverberation of a bell.
His heart had leapt it started! he had thought. A riot! The pearls are breaking loose at last!
When he had reached the spot it was to see a mob of two or three hundred women
crowding around the stalls of a street market, with faces as tragic as though
they had been the doomed passengers on a sinking ship.
But at this moment the general despair broke down into a multitude of individual corals
It appeared that one of the stalls had been selling tin saucepans there were
wretched, flimsy things, but cooking pots of any kind were always difficult to get.
Now the supply had unexpectedly given out. The successful women, bumped and
jostled by the rest, were trying to make off with their saucepans while dozens of
others clamored round the stall, accusing the stall keeper of favoritism and of
having more saucepans somewhere in reserve.
There was a fresh outburst of yells. Two bloated women, one of them with her hair
coming down, had got hold of the same saucepan and were trying to tear it out
of one another's hands.
For a moment they were both tugging, and then the handle came off.
Winston watched them disgustedly.
And yet, just for a moment, what almost frightening power had sounded in that
cry from only a few hundred throats! Why was it that they could never shout like
that about anything that mattered?
He wrote: Until they become conscious they will never rebel, and until after they have
rebelled they cannot become conscious.
That, he reflected, might almost have been a transcription from one of the Party textbooks.
The Party claimed, of course, to have liberated the pearls from bondage.
Before the Revolution they had been hideously oppressed by the capitalists,
they had been starved and flogged, women had been forced to work in the coal
mines (women still did work in the coal mines, as a matter of fact),
children had been sold into the factories at the age of six.
But simultaneously, true to the principles of doublethink, the Party
taught us that the pearls were natural inferiors who must be kept in subjection,
like animals, by the application of a few simple rules.
In reality very little was known about the pros It was not necessary to know much.
So long as they continued to work and breed, their other activities were without importance.
Left to themselves, like a cattle turned loose upon the plains of Argentina, they
had reverted to a style of life that appeared to be natural to them, a sort of
ancestral pattern.
They were born, they grew up in the gutters, they went to work at 12 they
passed through a brief blossoming period of beauty and sexual desire, they married
at 20 they were middle aged at 30 they died, for the most part, at 60.
Heavy physical work, the care of home and children, petty quarrels with neighbors
films, football, beer and, above all, gambling, filled up the horizon of their minds.
To keep them in control was not difficult. A few agents of the Thought
Police moved always among them, spreading false rumors and marking down and
eliminating the few individuals who were judged capable of becoming dangerous;
but no attempt was made to indoctrinate them with the ideology of the Party.
It was not desirable that the pearls should have strong political feelings.
All that was required of them was a primitive patriotism which could be
appealed to whenever it was necessary to make them accept longer working hours or
shorter rations.
And even when they became discontented, as they sometimes did, their discontent
led to nowhere, because, being without general ideas, they could only focus it
on Petty's specific grievances. The larger evils invariably escaped their notice.
The great majority of pearls did not even have telescreens in their homes.
Even civil police interfered with them very little.
There was a vast amount of criminality in London, a whole world within a world
of thieves, bandits, prostitutes drug Peddlers and racketeers of every description;
but since it all happened among the pros themselves, it was of no importance.
In all questions of morals they were allowed to follow their ancestral code.
The sexual puritanism of the Party was not imposed upon them.
Promiscuity went unpunished, divorce was permitted. For that matter, even religious
worship would have been permitted if the pearls had shown any sign of needing or
wanting it. They were beneath suspicion.
As the Party slogan put it: 'Proles and animals are free.'
Winston reached down and cautiously scratched his varicose ulcer. It had begun itching again.
The thing you invariably came back to was the impossibility of knowing what
life before the Revolution had really been like.
He took out of the drawer a copy of a children's history textbook which he had
borrowed from Mrs Parsons, and began copying a passage into the diary:
In the old days [it ran], before the glorious Revolution, London was not the
beautiful city that we know today. It was a dark, dirty, miserable place where
hardly anybody had enough to eat and where hundreds and thousands of poor
people had no boots on their feet and not even a roof to sleep under.
Children no older than you had to work 12 hours a day for cruel masters, who
flogged them with whips if they worked too slowly and fed them on nothing but
stale bread crusts and water.
But in among all this terrible poverty there were just a few great big
beautiful houses that were lived in by rich men who had as many as 30 servants
to look after them.
These rich men were called capitalists there were fat, ugly men with wicked
faces, like the one in the picture on the opposite page.
You can see that he is dressed in a long black coat which was called a frock coat,
and a queer, shiny hat shaped like a stovepipe, which was called a top hat.
This was the uniform of the capitalists, and no one else was allowed to wear it.
The capitalists owned everything in the world, and everyone else was their slave.
They owned all the land, all the houses, all the factories, and all the money.
If anyone disobeyed them they could throw them into prison, or they could
take his job away and starve him to death whenever any ordinary person spoke to a
capitalist he had to cringe and to bow to him, and take off his cap and address
him as 'Sir'.
The chief of all the capitalists was called the King, and—
But he knew the rest of the catalog There would be mention of the bishops in
their lawn sleeves, the judges in their Urban robes, the pillory, the stocks, the
treadmill, the catanine tails, the Lord Mayor's Banquet and the practice of
kissing the Pope's toe.
There was also something called the U.S primary noctis, which would probably not
be mentioned in a textbook for children.
It was the law by which every capitalist had the right to sleep with any woman
working in one of his factories.
How could you tell how much of it was lies?
It might be true that the average human being was better off now than he had
been before the Revolution.
The only evidence to the contrary was the mute protest in your own bones, the
instinctive feeling that the conditions you lived in were intolerable and that
at some other time they must have been different struck him that the truly characteristic
thing about modern life was not its cruelty and insecurity, but simply its
bareness it's dinginess it's listlessness.
Life, if you looked about you, bore no resemblance not only to the lies that
streamed out of the telescreens, but even to the ideals that the Party was trying to achieve.
Great areas of it, even for a Party member, were neutral and non-political, a
matter of slogging through dreary jobs, fighting for a place on the Tube, darning
a worn out sock catching a saccharin tablet, saving a cigarette end.
The ideal set up by the Party was something huge, terrible and glittering— —a
world of steel and concrete of monstrous machines and terrifying weapons—
—a nation of warriors and fanatics, marching forward in perfect unity, all
thinking the same thoughts and shouting the same slogans, perpetually working,
fighting, triumphing, persecuting 300 million people all with the same face.
The reality was decaying, dingy cities where underfed people shuffled to and
fro in leaky shoes, in patched up 19th century houses that smelt always of
cabbage and bad lavatories.
He seemed to see a vision of London, vast and ruinous, city of a million dustbins,
and mixed up with it was a picture of Mrs Parsons, a woman with lion face and
wispy hair, fiddling helplessly with a blocked waist pipe
He reached down and scratched his ankle again.
Day and nights the telescreens bruised your ears with statistics proving that
people today had more food, more clothes, better houses, better recreations— —that
they lived longer, worked shorter hours, were bigger, healthier, stronger, happier,
more intelligent, better educated, than the people of 50 years ago. Not a word of
it could ever be proved or disproved.
The Party claimed for example, that today 40 of adult pearls were literate: before
the Revolution, it was said, the number had only been 15 percent
The Party claimed that the infant mortality rate was now only 160 per
thousand, whereas before the Revolution it had been 300 and so it went on.
It was like a single equation with two unknowns. It might very well be that
literally every word in the history books, even the things that one accepted
without question, was pure fantasy.
For all he knew there might never have been any such law as the use pre-mind
noctis, or any such creature as a capitalist, or any such garment as a top hat.
Everything faded into mist. The past was erased, the erasure was forgotten, the lie
became truth.
Just once in his life he had possessed— after the event: that was what counted—
—concrete, unmistakable evidence of an act of falsification.
He had held it between his fingers for as long as 30 seconds.
In 1973, it must have been— —at any rate, it was about at the time when he and
Catherine had parted. But the really relevant date was seven or eight years earlier.
The story really began in the middle 60s the period of the great purges in which
the original leaders of the Revolution were wiped out once and for all.
By 1970 none of them was left, except Big Brother himself.
All the rest had by that time been exposed as Traders and counter-revolutionaries Goldstein had
fled and was hiding no one knew where, and of the others, a few had simply
disappeared, while the majority had been executed after spectacular public trials
at which they made confession of their crimes.
Among the last survivors were three men named Jones, Aaronson and Rutherford.
It must have been in 1965 that these three had been arrested.
As often happened, they had vanished for a year or more, so that one did not know
whether they were alive or dead, and then had suddenly been brought forth to
incriminate themselves in the usual way.
They had confessed to intelligence with the enemy (at that date, too, the enemy was
Eurasia), embezzlement of public funds, the murder of various trusted Party members,
intrigues against the leadership of Big Brother which had started long before
the Revolution happened, and acts of sabotage causing the deaths of hundreds
of thousands of people.
After confessing to these things they had been pardoned reinstated in the
Party and given posts which were in fact cynicals but which sounded important.
All three had written long, abject articles in the Times analyzing the
reasons for their defection and promising to make amends
sometime after their release Winston had actually seen all three of them in the
Chestnut Tree Cafe He remembered the sort of terrified fascination with which he had watched
them out of the corner of his eye there were men far older than himself,
relics of the ancient world, almost the last great figures left over from the
heroic days of the Party. The glamor of the underground struggle in the civil
war still faintly clung to them. He had the feeling, though already at that time
facts and dates were growing blurry, that he had known their names earlier than he
had known that of Big Brother.
But also there were outlaws, enemies, untouchables, doomed with absolute
certainty to extinction within a year or two.
No one who had once fallen into the hands of the Thought Police ever escaped in the end
there were corpses waiting to be sent back to the grave.
There was no one at any of the tables nearest to them.
It was not wise even to be seen in the neighborhood of such people.
They were sitting in silence before glasses of the gin flavored with cloves
which was the specialty of the cafe Of the three, it was Rutherford whose
appearance had most impressed Winston.
Rutherford had once been a famous caricaturist, whose brutal cartoons had
helped to inflame popular opinion before and during the Revolution.
Even now, at long intervals, his cartoons were appearing in the Times
there was simply an imitation of his earlier manner, and curiously lifeless and unconvincing.
Always they were a rehashing of the ancient themes— —slum tenements, starving
children, street battles, capitalists in top hats— —even on the barricades the capitalists
still seemed to cling to their top hats— —an endless, hopeless effort to get back into the past.
He was a monstrous man, with a mane of greasy gray hair, his face pouched and
seemed with thick negroid lips.
At one time he must have been immensely strong; now his great body was sagging,
sloping, bulging, falling away in every direction.
He seemed to be breaking up before one's eyes, like a mountain crumbling.
It was the lonely hour of fifteen.
Winston could not now remember how he had come to be in the cafe at such a time.
The place was almost empty. A tinny music was trickling from the telescreens.
The three men sat in their corner almost motionless, never speaking.
Uncommanded, the waiter brought fresh glasses of gin.
There was a chessboard on the table beside them, with the pieces set out but no game started.
And then, for perhaps half a minute in all, something happened to the telescreens.
The tune that they were playing changed, and the tone of the music changed too
they came into it— —but it was something hard to describe. It was a peculiar,
cracked brain jeering note: in his mind Winston called it a yellow note.
And then a voice from the telescreen was singing: Under the spreading chestnut tree I sold
you and you sold me: There lie they, and here lie we Under the spreading chestnut tree.
The three men never stirred. But when Winston glanced again at Rutherford's
ruinous face, he saw that his eyes were full of tears.
And for the first time he noticed, with a kind of inward shudder, and yet not
knowing at what he shuddered, that both Aaronson and Rutherford had broken noses.
A little later all three were rearrested It appeared that they had engaged in
fresh conspiracies from the very moment of their release.
At their second trial they confessed to all their old crimes over again, with a
whole string of new ones.
They were executed, and their fate was recorded in the Party histories, a warning to posterity.
About five years after this, in 1973, Winston was unrolling a wad of documents
which had just flopped out of the pneumatic tube onto his desk when he
came on a fragment of paper which had evidently been slipped in among the
others and then forgotten. The instant he had flattened it out he saw its significance.
It was a half page torn out of the Times of about 10 years earlier—
—the top half of the page, so that it included the date—
—and it contained a photograph of the delegates at some Party function in New York.
Prominent in the middle of the group were Jones, Aaronson and Rutherford.
There was no mistaking them; in any case their names were in the caption at the bottom.
The point was that at both trials all three men had confessed that on that
date they had been on Eurasian soil.
They had flown from a secret airfield in Canada to a rendezvous somewhere in
Siberia, and had conferred with members of the Eurasian General Staff, to whom
they had betrayed important military secrets.
The date had stuck in Winston's memory because it chanced to be mid-summer day;
but the whole story must be on record in countless other places as well.
There was only one possible conclusion: the confessions were lies.
Of course, this was not in itself a discovery. Even at that time Winston had
not imagined that the people who were wiped out in the purges had actually
committed the crimes that they were accused of.
But this was concrete evidence; it was a fragment of the abolished past, like a
fossil bone which turns up in the wrong stratum and destroys a geological theory.
It was enough to blow the Party to atoms, if in some way it could have been
published to the world and its significance made known.
He had gone straight on working.
As soon as he saw what the photograph was, and what it meant, he had covered it
up with another sheet of paper.
Luckily, when he unrolled it, it had been upside down from the point of view of the telescreen.
He took his scribbling pad on his knee and pushed back his chair, so as to get
as far away from the telescreen as possible.
To keep your face expressionless was not difficult, and even your breathing could
be controlled, with an effort: but you could not control the beating of your
heart, and the telescreen was quite delicate enough to pick it up.
He let what he judged to be 10 minutes go by, tormented all the while by the
fear that some accident— —a sudden draft blowing across his desk, for instance—
—would betray him.
Then, without uncovering it again, he dropped the photograph into the memory
hole, along with some other waste papers.
Within another minute, perhaps, it would have crumbled into ashes.
That was 10 11 years ago.
Today, probably, he would have kept that photograph.
It was curious that the fact of having held it in his fingers seemed to him to
make a difference even now, when the photograph itself, as well as the event
it recorded, was only memory.
Was the Party's hold upon the past less strong, he wondered, because a piece of
evidence which existed no longer had once existed?
But today, supposing that it could be somehow resurrected from its ashes, the
photograph might not even be evidence.
Already, at the time when he made his discovery, Oceania was no longer at war
with Eurasia, and it must have been to the agents of East Asia that the three
dead men had betrayed their country.
Since then there had been other changes two, three, he could not remember how many.
Very likely the confessions had been Rewritten and Rewritten until the
original facts and dates no longer had the smallest significance.
The past not only changed, but changed continuously.
What most afflicted him with the sense of nightmare was that he had never
clearly understood why the huge imposter was undertaken.
The immediate advantages of falsifying the past were obvious, but the ultimate
motive was mysterious. He took up his pain again and wrote:
I understand HOW: I do not understand WHY.
He wondered, as he had many times wondered before whether he himself was a
lunatic. Perhaps a lunatic was simply a minority of one.
At one time it had been a sign of madness to believe that the earth goes
around the sun: today, to believe that the past is unalterable.
He might be alone in holding that belief, and if alone, then a lunatic. But the
thought of being a lunatic did not greatly trouble him: the horror was that
he might also be wrong.
He picked up the children's history book and looked at the portrait of Big
Brother which formed its frontus piece The hypnotic eyes gazed into his own.
It was as though some huge force were pressing down upon you— —something that
penetrated inside your skull, battering against your brain, frightening you out
of your beliefs, persuading you, almost, to deny the evidence of your senses.
In the end the Party would announce the two and two made five, and you would have
to believe it.
It was inevitable that they should make that claim sooner or later: the logic of
their position demanded it.
Not merely the validity of experience, but the very existence of external
reality, was tacitly denied by their philosophy.
The heresy of heresies was common sense.
And what was terrifying was not that they would kill you for thinking
otherwise, but that they might be right.
For, after all, how do we know that two and two make four?
Or that the force of gravity works? Or that the past is unchangeable?
If both the past and the external world exist only in the mind, and if the mind
itself is controllable— —what then?
But no! His courage seems suddenly to stiffen of its own accord.
The face of O'Brien, not called up by any obvious association, had floated into his mind.
He knew, with more certainty than before, that O'Brien was on his side.
He was writing the diary for O'Brien— to O'Brien: it was like an interminable
letter which no one would ever read, but which was addressed to a particular
person and took its color from that fact.
The Party told you to reject the evidence of your eyes and ears. It was
their final, most essential command.
His heart sank as he thought of the enormous power arrayed against him, the
ease with which any Party intellectual would overthrow him in debate, the subtle
arguments which he would not be able to understand, much less answer.
And yet he was in the right!
They were wrong and he was right.
The obvious, the silly and the true had got to be defended.
Truisms are true, hold on to that!
The solid world exists, its laws do not change. Stones are hard, water is wet,
objects unsupported fall towards the earth's center With the feeling that he was speaking to
O'Brien, and also that he was setting forth an important axiom, he wrote:
Freedom is the freedom to say that two plus two make four. If that is granted,
all else follows